RG 124, Hartford City Guard
Connecticut State Library
Hartford City Guard records
1861-1917
Connecticut State Library
Harford (Conn.). City Guard
2 cubic feet
The Hartford City Guard was an Independent Company from January 8 to September 11, 1861. It then became Artillery Company A, 1st Regiment, Connecticut Militia, organizing under the captaincy of Charles H. Prentice. In 1863 it became an infantry company. Some Hartford City Guard officers joined the volunteer forces in the Civil War. The company was designated Company A, 4th Regiment, Connecticut Volunteers on May 16, 1861. Afterwards, it changed to First Connecticut Heavy Artillery, which was mustered into the U.S. service on May 22, 1861. On August 18, 1865, it became Battery D, Light Artillery, Connecticut National Guard, attached to the 1st Regiment. It was then attached to the 3rd Regiment from August 8 1867 to August 1, 1871. In 1871, it became Company F of the 1st Regiment, and it remains so today.
RG124
T001457
Historical Note
The Hartford City Guard was an Independent Company from January 8 to September 11, 1861. It then became Artillery Company A, 1st Regiment, Connecticut Militia, organizing under the captaincy of Charles H. Prentice. In 1863 it became an infantry company. Some Hartford City Guard officers joined the volunteer forces in the Civil War. The company was designated Company A, 4th Regiment, Connecticut Volunteers on May 16, 1861. Afterwards, it changed to First Connecticut Heavy Artillery, which was mustered into the U.S. service on May 22, 1861. On August 18, 1865, it became Battery D, Light Artillery, Connecticut National Guard, attached to the 1st Regiment. (In 1865 the term "Militia" was dropped and "Connecticut National Guard" was substituted). It was then attached to the 3rd Regiment from August 8 1867 to August 1, 1871. In 1871, it became Company F of the 1st Regiment, and it remains so today.
Some of the captains of the Hartford City Guard were: Charles H. Prentice, 1861-1863; Solomon P. Conners, 1863; John K. Williams, 1863-1869; John L. White, 1869-1880; Levi H. Hotchkiss, 1880-1882; Charles E. Thompson, 1882-1884.
Scope and Content
The records consist of applications for membership, constitution and by-laws, contracts and agreements, financial records, minutes of meetings, special orders, and other similar materials.
Related Material
RG 118, Veteran Association of the Hartford City Guard.
Additional records of the Hartford City Guard will be found among the papers of the Connecticut National Guard. Discharges of Company F and Battery D are among these.
Separated Material
Two volumes of The Knapsack, 1873-1875, published by City Guard [CSL call number StLib Special Collections AN104.H3 K63] and on microfilm at [CSL call number StLib Newspaper Room AN104.H3 K63].
Index Terms
Organizations:
Hartford (Conn.). City Guard
Subjects:
Hartford (Conn.). City Guard -- Records and correspondence; Connecticut -- Militia
Document Types:
Bylaws (administrative records); Constitutions; Correspondence; Financial records; Clippings; Membership lists; Resolutions; Reports; Minutes
Restrictions on Access
See the policy.
Container List
- Records, 1861-1917
  - Constitution and by-laws of the Hartford City Guard, 1861 (Box 1)
    Also includes original roll of the Company, May 1, 1861.
  - Original preamble and constitution adopted January 8, 1861, manuscript (Box 1)
  - Contracts, agreements, bonds, leases, 1861-1865, 1879, 1883 (Box 1)
  - History and minutes, 1888-1889 (Box 1)
  - Invoices, 1871, 1877 (Box 1)
  - Receipted bills, 1865 (Box 1)
  - Treasurers' reports, 1866 January 1-1868 January 20 (Box 1)
  - Receipted bills, 1867-1871 (Box 1)
  - Treasurers' reports, 1871-1873 (Box 1)
  - Receipts, 1872-1877 (Box 1)
  - Treasurers' and collectors' reports, 1874-1877 (Box 1)
  - Treasurers' reports, 1878-1879 (Box 1)
  - Treasurers' reports and receipted bills, 1880 (Box 1)
  - Treasurers' and collectors' reports, 1881-1882 (Box 1)
  - Treasurers' and collectors' reports, 1883-1884 (Box 1)
  - Treasurers' reports and collectors' reports, 1888 (Box 1)
  - Treasurers' reports and collectors' reports, 1889 (Box 1)
  - Receipted bills, 1889 (Box 1)
  - Treasurers' report, 1901 January 14 (Box 1)
  - Treasurers' reports and collectors' reports, 1905 April-1906 October (Box 1)
  - Treasurers' report and collectors' reports, 1907 (Box 1)
  - Receipted bills, 1907 (Box 1)
  - Collectors' reports, 1908 (Box 1)
  - Receipted bills, 1908 (Box 1)
  - Treasurers' reports and collectors' reports, 1909 (Box 1)
  - Receipted bills, 1909 (Box 1)
  - Treasurers' reports and collectors' reports, 1910 (Box 1)
  - Receipted bills, 1910 (Box 1)
  - Collectors' reports, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Receipted bills, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Receipted bills, 1912-1913 (Box 1)
  - Reports of committees, 1867 (Box 1)
    Includes Committee on Decorations for Reunion and Committee on Promenade Concert.
  - Reports of committees, 1876, 1878, 1879 (Box 1)
    Includes Committees on Centennial Parade, Reception of 1st Light Infantry, Estimate of expense for encampment at Martha's Vineyard.
  - Reports of committees, 1881-1882 (Box 1)
    Includes Committees on Purchase of Company Album, Obtaining Prices for Photographs, and Testimonials.
  - Reports of Committees, 1884 (Box 1)
    Includes reports of Committees on Membership, Armory, and Day in Camp.
  - Reports of committees, 1888 (Box 1)
    Includes Armory and Membership.
  - Reports of Armory Committee, 1889 (Box 1)
  - Report of Sociable Committee, 1889 (Box 1)
    Also includes receipts.
  - Report of Committee on Souvenir Badges, 1889 (Box 1)
  - Report of Committee on Past-Members Accounts, 1901 January 12 (Box 1)
  - Resolutions, 1865-1889 (Box 1)
  - Circulars, 1864-1889 (Box 2)
  - Orders & valuable papers wanted for constant reference, 1866-1870 (Box 2)
    Includes circulars re: uniform, inspection, requisition, inventory and orders.
  - Company orders, 1862-1864, 1881-1882, 1914 (Box 2)
  - General orders, 1862-1866 (Box 2)
  - General orders, 1868-1875, 1881 (Box 2)
  - Special orders, 1863-1867 (Box 2)
  - Special orders, 1868-1869 (Box 2)
  - Special orders, 1870-1871 (Box 2)
  - Special orders, 1875 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Capt. Charles Prentice, Artillery Co. A, 1st Regt. Conn. Militia, 1861-1864 (Box 2)
    - Capt. John K. Williams, Hartford City Guard, 1865-1866 (Box 2)
    - Capt. John K. Williams, Hartford City Guard, 1867 (Box 2)
    - Capt. John K. Williams, Hartford City Guard - Commanding Battery D, C.N.G., 1868 (Box 2)
    - Albert Fox, Secretary, Hartford City Guard, 1869 (Box 2)
    - Capt. John White, Commanding Battery D, C.N.G. et al, 1869 (Box 2)
    - Albert Fox, Secretary, Hartford City Guard, 1870 (Box 2)
    - Albert Fox, Secretary, Hartford City Guard, 1872 (Box 2)
    - Capt. John L. White, Commanding Co. F, 1st Regiment, Conn. National Guard, et al, 1872 (Box 2)
    - Capt. John L. White, et al (Miscellaneous), 1878-1879 (Box 2)
    - Capt. John L. White regarding sale of old uniforms, 1879 (Box 2)
    - Capt. John L. White et al, 1880-1881 (Box 2)
    - Capt. Charles E. Thompson, commanding Hartford City Guard, 1883-1884 (Box 2)
    - E.H. Young, Secretary, Hartford City Guard, 1884 (Box 2)
    - Capt. George B. Newton, Commanding Co. F, 1st Regiment, 1888-1889 (Box 2)
    - Capt. George W. Ripley, Commanding Co. F, 1st Regt. C.N.G., 1899 (Box 2)
    - Co. F, 1st Infantry, C.N.G., 1905-1907 (Box 2)
    - Capt. Frederick A. Seidler, Commanding Co. F, 1st Infantry, C.N.G., 1908 (Box 2)
    - Co. F, 1st Infantry, C.N.G., 1909-1917 (Box 2)
  - Propositions for membership, Hartford City Guard, Co. F, 1st Regiment, C.N.G. (Box 2)
    - 1876-1877 (Box 2)
    - 1878-1879 (Box 2)
    - 1880-1881 (Box 2)
    - 1882-1883 (Box 2)
    - 1886, undated (Box 2)
  - Applications for Enlistment (Box 2)
    - Co. H, 1st Regiment, 1878 (Box 2)
    - Co. F 1st Regiment, C.N.G., 1902-1904 (Box 2)
  - Monthly report of gain and loss (Co. F, 1st Regiment), 1902-1906 (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets (Box 2)
    Includes "Experience of a Recruit in the United States Army", 1916 and pamphlet of forms, returns, uniform.
  - Clippings from newspapers (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous folder, 1880-1917, undated (Box 2)
    Various handwritten notes, few announcements, lists, etc.
  - Quarterly returns of ordnance and ordnance stores, Co. F, 1904 (Box 2)
  - Ordnance property forms, Co. F, 1897-1917 (Box 2)
  - Election certificate for A.B. Gillette, 1865 March (Box 2)